Katy Ilonka Gero

www.katygero.com ~ katy@cs.columbia.edu

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science Sep 2017 – current

Columbia University Advisor: Lydia Chilton

M.S. in Computer Science Sep 2017 – May 2019

Columbia University

B.S. in Mechanical Engineering Sep 2009 – May 2013

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Research Statement

I am interested in computational tools that support complex and creative tasks, with a focus on writing forms like poetry, journalism, and science writing. I design tools that use AI methods in novel and sometimes unexpected ways. I want to understand how we can use these methods to augment our abilities, rather than replace them, and consider the ethical implications of this goal, such as how to develop AI systems capable of responding to a range of inputs safely, and our feelings of ownership and agency when using them.

Research areas: *Human-Computer Interaction, Human-AI Interaction, Natural Language Processing*

Publications

Full Conference Publications

K. Gero, V. Liu, S. Huang, J. Lee, T. Requarth, L. Chilton. "What Makes Tweetorials Tick: How Experts Communicate Complex Topics on Twitter" in *Proceedings of the 21st ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing (CSCW '21).*[In Submission]

K. Gero, Z. Ashktorab, C. Dugan, Q. Pan, J. Johnson, W. Geyer, M. Ruiz, S. Miller, D. Millen, W. Geyer. "Mental Models of AI Agents in a Cooperative Game Setting" in *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20)*. [CHI Best Paper]

K. Gero, C. Kedzie, J. Reeve, L. Chilton. "Low-Level Linguistic Controls for Style Transfer and Content Preservation" in *Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Natural Language Generation (INLG '19).*

K. Gero, L. Chilton. "Metaphoria: An Algorithmic Companion for Metaphor Creation" in *Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '19).*

Workshop Papers and Posters

A. Calderwood, V. Qiu, **K. Gero**, and L. Chilton. "How Novelists Use Generative Language Models: An Exploratory User Study" in 1st Workshop on Human-AI Co-Creation with Generative Models (IUI '20).

K. Gero, L. Chilton. "How a Stylistic, Machine-Generated Thesaurus Impacts a Writer's Process" in *Proceedings of the 2019 on Creativity & Cognition (C&C '19)*.

K. Gero, L. Chilton. "Challenges in Finding Metaphorical Connections" in *Proceedings of the Workshop on Figurative Language Processing (NAACL '18)*.

Employment

IBM Research, Research Intern
Cambridge, MA
Mentor: Zahra Ashktorab

Soofa, Research & Development Lead
Cambridge, MA
Soofa creates technology for cities, like solar-powered transit signs.

Managed research projects on the Soofa Platform.

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019

Mar 2016 - Aug 2017

Rest Devices, Product Developer

Aug 2013 - Mar 2016

Boston, MA

Rest Devices designed and manufactured a soft, wearable baby monitor. *Oversaw manufacturing; designed and implemented new algorithms.*

Awards & Recognition

Magic Grant, \$65k The Brown Institute for Media Innovation	2019 - 2020
Graduate Research Fellowship Program Fellow National Science Foundation	2017 - 2022
Seed Grant for Interdisciplinary Research, \$1.8k Center for Science & Society Columbia University	2018
Graduate Student Digital Project Honorable Mention, \$500 NYC Digital Humanities	2018
Provost's Diversity Fellowship, \$6k Columbia University	2017 - 2018

Carl G. Sontheimer Prize for Excellence in Innovation and Creativity Department of Mechanical Engineering Massachusetts Institute for Technology	2013
Invited Talks	
Technology for Writing AI4ALL, Guest Speaker Virtual	2020
Technology for Writing Ignition Hacks, Guest Speaker Virtual	2020
Technology for Writing Columbia University , Demystifying the Dissertation Speaker Virtual	2020
Re-Generating Text with Style CultureHub Re-Fest , Speaker & Panelist New York, New York	2020
Semantic Tools for Writers Computational Models and Mimesis Symposium , Speaker & Participant Dartmouth College, Hanover, New Hampshire	2019
AI Tools for Creative Writing Grammarly , NLP Meeting Speaker New York, New York	2019
Words, words, words, style, words, words, words, and words Babycastles , WordHack Featured Artist New York, New York	2019
Community Service	
Mentor for BEARS Research Program for Women Barnard College Run monthly meetings with five undergrads to demystify research.	2021
Organizer of Pre-Application Review Program for PhD Applicants Department of Computer Science, Columbia University Coordinated with Dean's office and led outreach efforts.	2020 – 2021
Organizer for Bits4Justice Department of Computer Science, Columbia University Run bi-monthly meetings organizing student racial justice activism.	2020 - current

Academic Chair for Women in Computer Science (WiCS) Club Columbia University Ran events to introduce undergraduates to research.	2019 - 2020
Professional Service	
Co-Organizer Workshop on Human-AI Co-Creation with Generative Models Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI)	2020, 2021
Reviewer for CHI, UIST, CSCW, DIS, C&C	Since 2020
Involvement in the Arts	
Resident Contributing Writer, CultureHub An Introduction to Feedback Computing Outside the Feedback Loop	2020 - 2021
Poetry Fellow, Brooklyn Poets Poet-of-the-Week Reading and Interview	2020
Select Poetry	
WHALEFALL in taper Self-Portrait as a Decision Tree in Bookstore Poets Vol. 1 The Cloud in The Blueshift Journal	2020 2019 2015
Select Essays What Kind of Sonnets Will Computers Write? in Catapult Language and the Algorithm in Ploughshares blog Is It Possible for Machines to Translate Poetry? in Electric Literature Why Siri Sounds Like a Girl in SheCanCode	2020 2018 2018 2017